[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software hey innovators the i e computer
society's door is wide open for your
next big idea with the emerging Tech
grants program dream big and you can
land funding between 25 and 50k jump on
this chance at our website computer.org
dgrs that's computer.org
dgrs hey this is Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio today I'm
talking to iness montani she's the
co-founder and CEO of explosion which is
a company specializing in developer
tools for machine learning and natural
language processing she's also a core
developer of the Spacey NLP library and
The Prodigy annotation tool iness
welcome to software engineering radio
yeah hi thanks for having me very
excited so I think the first thing we
could start with is defining NLP so what
is NLP for people who aren't familiar
yeah I mean it's a good question because
actually you know if you look around on
the Internet or follow the field you
might actually find slightly different
definitions I would describe it as
processing large volumes of text so you
have have text and you want to find
something out about that text and more
recently A lot of people have also
included a more General natural language
understanding in the term NLP so even
you know you have a chatbot that
generates text something like chat GPT
which most people are familiar with
that's usually also defined under that
umbrella even though you know it's a
slightly different task than really just
processing the text but basically I
think the underlying question is there's
text and you want to use a computer to
do something with it that's NLP in some
of your talks there's sort of two
categories I think you put problems into
one is generative and then yep
predictive okay yeah and I think that
was also something kind of in response
to yeah maybe people even been bit
confused about like what's NLP and maybe
mostly thinking about the generative
part and not so much about the
predictive part where you know you
extract structured data from text even
though I would say it's actually still
probably in industry and in production
the main area of NLP that is used
especially in companies because there's
just so much unstructured text and
there's so many cases where you want to
get the text into a format that you can
compute with or work with so I thought
that distinction was very important and
can you give some specific examples of
what are some generative things and what
are some predictive examp yes generative
it's of course something classic like
talking to a dialogue system like a
chatboard question question answering
translation that's also a task where
text goes in text comes out and then
predictive is really more things along
the lines of information extraction like
you have a text and you want to or you
have emails that are coming in and you
want to decide are these emails spam is
it about billing that's like what
usually would be referred to as text
classification so you assign one label
to the whole text or then there are
other tasks where you're really
extracting spans of texts like person
names organization
phrases and so on from text that's also
an area of information extraction and
really an area where you predict
something and very structured
information based on unstructured text
and so it sounds like generative is
something where you're creating new text
I suppose and predictive is more you
want to know something or learn
something about text that's already
there is that kind of accurate yeah
that's you put it like that and also
often for predictive what's important is
that what you want to find out about a
text you want to map that back into the
text like you want to know where are
these person names what are they how are
they related to each other how are they
used often you also want to Stack these
things on top of each other like you
want to start by maybe deciding what
spam and then for everything that's not
spam you want to extract what department
is it about and then based on that if
it's about that department and it's
about billing what's the invoice amount
mentioned in the invoice and so in the
email and so on so there's like often
they really is a pipeline of steps that
you want to apply that can depend on
each other and that each have different
requirements and different difficulties
some of them you can maybe use rules for
you can connect it to your database and
other things are like much more complex
and nuanced and then other things you
actually don't even need machine
learning for because you can just use a
regular expression or just write it in
code so yeah there's like a lot of a lot
of different things people are trying to
do and since your company started as a a
consultancy for NLP work can you give
some examples of projects that your your
company took on just so that people can
get a sense of what are NLP problems I
suppose yeah so I mean there's a lot we
actually still do Consulting
occasionally because we feel like it's
actually very important to stay close to
the use cases because if you're
developing tools for people that should
solve a problem for them you want to
make sure that you're actually solving
your own problems with the technology so
we still have projects like that and to
give examples one common topic or use
case is extracting certain information
from news and then feeding that into an
internal knowledge Bas so you might have
a company that even stuff like a company
wants to find out whether something in
their supply chain
or in someone else's supply chain might
be impacted and cause them a lot of
problems that's like it's kind of a yeah
sounds like a boring use case but it's
like if you think about it it's like
insanely valuable so then what do you do
you want to scrape news and find out
that hey there's a strike in this small
town here and that might later come back
to us via these Channel something like
that or you want to analyze financial
documents about Acquisitions and mergers
who was bought what amounts and then at
the end of it you might want to compute
things like which emerging areas are
there how many Acquisitions did Apple do
in that time frame and so on so that's
like really classic information
extraction work and that's also actually
a lot of what we're seeing in the
projects that people are trying to solve
you have a library that your company
built called Spacey and I wonder if you
could talk about within the context of
Spacey and then maybe the things you
need to use around it how would you
start to approach a problem like that
where you have all this unstructured
data you have news reports you're
bringing in you have these Financial
reports where do you get started in in
the process yeah so actually that step
of really deciding what to do is really
the hard part like often people might
think about training a model and all of
this like o algorithm stuff but all of
that is pretty straightforward these
days the hard part is really starting
out and deciding what to do and trying
things out and there it's really like
software development or coding like the
first line of code you write is rarely
the one you're going to ship to
production so you need to iterate
refactor try things out and it's very
similar with data so usually you know
first step even before you get into any
of the tools is thinking about what do
you want the system to do that's like um
sounds simple but it's really the
fundamental problem that we all trying
to solve we have a computer and a
computer should do a thing how do we get
the computer to do exactly what we want
how do we describe that so one approach
for that if you have a lot of data a lot
of raw data is to just create labeled
examples so you take that data you
annotate here are all company
Acquisitions filter the right examples
out label the spans of text that you're
interested in and go through that and
you definitely even if you're using
approaches that don't train on labeled
data you always need that kind of Step
because you need to have a source of
Truth you need to have a way to evaluate
your system a lot of people don't do
that but like if you're thinking about
best practices it's like a lot of people
don't write tests when they write code
that's like a thing but we all know that
that's not something we should do we all
need to write tests and it's the same
with like an evaluation set so you want
to basically start out and create
examples where you know the answer so
you can test your approaches and that's
already where things can get tricky even
before you get tooling involved because
you'll realize that language doesn't so
neatly divide into categories as you
know you may be naively thought and so
you'll have edge cases you need to
decide what do I do with them what
labels do I want how do I want to divide
up the problem that's all the work
that's challenging and that I would say
most people people struggle with the
most and often that takes experience
that takes trying things out and then
also picking the right component you
want to train is this a problem where it
makes sense to predict something over
the whole text or is it a problem where
it makes sense to extract spans of text
what kinds of spans of text do you want
to extract and so on this like there are
a lot of these decisions where often you
just have to try things out and where
maybe your first idea or the naive idea
isn't the right way forward so that's
all so assuming you have all that
process you know you have decided what
you want it makes sense it's something
that actually works in your data
then you can start picking up the tools
assembling your pipeline so Spacey
really is a library that was designed
with these multi-step pipeline workflows
in mind and really also optimized for
production usage so it's really really
fast you can train very small models
that are very specific to what you want
to do you can combine them with maybe
rules or knowledge bases you have and if
you have your data ready if you know
what you want to train then the actual
training can actually be pretty
straightforward and can really just be a
command that you run get your model out
and use it but the path to getting there
that's what's tricky and that's also
yeah that's also why this is the one
area that we really work on we have been
working on and also in future projects
we're working on that's really what we
want to tackle how can we make that
process easier and also easier for
non-experts who don't have a machine
learning background yeah so it sounds
like the very first step is taking what
seems like maybe a vague problem where
you're saying I want to know are there
things happening in the world that are
going to affect my business right which
is a very broad question so you start
with okay I'm going to bring in all this
unstructured data I'm going to write an
application maybe to scrape news sites
and get me all these documents but then
you have to break it down into these
more specific I don't know if questions
is the right word prediction problems I
think that's why we would call it and
also yeah I think you quickly see that
your business problems don't actually
translate into onetoone prediction
problems and so the very start would be
deciding okay maybe I need to be able to
read these documents and determine what
are these documents talking about and
then is it like a positive thing or is
it a negative thing and then kind of
classifying all these things and or even
is it like what does positive or
negative mean right like one example was
I think someone was trying also you know
trying a similar model for like um news
and things that are happening reputation
management like basically how do people
talk about my brand good or bad but and
then they had this idea that well if
people say bad things about the
competitor then that's good for us and
we want to extract that as positive but
that is something that's like without
the context of your product and
everything else that's like not
something that really translates into
prediction problem the model has no idea
idea or if you label it that way and try
to teach the model that the model will
really really struggle to make sense of
this concept that why is this negative
sentiment suddenly G and so these are
all important things you want to tackle
before you actually get into the data
yeah so can you give a specific example
of a customer that you worked with and
how they broke down the problems or or
how they broke down okay I need to
classify this and classify this and this
is how I will use it as you know the end
result yeah I mean often it really
depends on the specific problem and it
also often you have to try things out
but you know a lot of it comes down to
really thinking about okay what is the
structured output that I want and how
easy SL hard is it going to be for the
model to finally produce that output and
often again that's like something where
either you have to have done it before
or you have you know have to be able to
try things out there definitely there
was one case that I think we're also
going to publish as a case study where
you know it was it's a financial use
case they wanted to extract a lot of
extremely specific terminology you know
kind of on a level of where you read the
sentence and you're like I get that
these are all words but I have no idea
what this is saying but they're like
over 30 attributes in this text needs to
be processed almost in real time needs
to be extracted and the first thing they
did was separate out these attributes
into things where the value can only be
one of a certain type or like an enum
basically and then everything else that
needs to be predicted so for the enums
well that's pretty straightforward you
can just provide a list of rules or
examples or even something more abstract
and then the other ones well you have to
create some data for them and you know
look at them in context and so initially
what they did was well we want to only
go through every example once let's cure
it all up for annotation and annotate
all 30 attributes together create some
data that way push ourselves through
that tedious process and it was
basically not possible to do that
efficiently at all because you have to
mentally focus on 30 different decisions
constantly switched between them so the
process was really slow and then after
looking at again at it again they were
like well let's try doing one label at a
time and really focusing on working
through that and sounds like a lot more
work at first because you know for 30
labels you need to look at every example
30 times but it actually turned into a
process that was more than 10 times
faster overall because you reduce the
cognitive load on the person creating
the data so I thought that was a pretty
interesting example because that stuff
also matters and that's I think also
what often keeps people from even going
down the route of looking at the data in
the first place because it feels like
this incredibly tedious
click work when a lot of it is just
about how you structure it and maybe
coming up with more creative and smarter
ways of looking at your data because I
think overall going by example is still
a great way of telling a computer what
to do in a way I think it has a lot of
advantages over writing prompts like
people know from say chaty PT or similar
models but it's currently a lot harder
so whereas prompts are very accessible
anyone can just write something and have
to model do it creating examples
training a model is a lot more work and
so that's actually why this is the area
we find like super exciting because
we're like okay how can we take this
expert work workflow that is Superior in
a lot of ways but make it almost as
straightforward as writing a prompt and
that example you gave of you have these
30 potential labels you can give to a
text can you specifically speak to are
they looking at a a sentence or are they
looking at a paragraph and then they're
they're just labeling that one thing or
or what spans of text so it's a
financial analyst writes something
that's happening in the market and
there's like a lot of this specific
terminology around how much what market
like it's again it's one of these things
where if you don't have a background in
finance you're like what it's barely
English but that's how the data comes in
and then ideally in real time you also
want to have a structured format of it
and you can't make your analysts do this
differently because they're already
reporting their things as fast as they
can but you can potentially build a
system that can handle it and they
actually managed to build an incredibly
fast pipeline that's super small like 6
megabyte model which you know especially
nowadays is like wo it runs entirely
private which is another advantage of
really being being able to build your
own systems because you don't need an
API you can run it in house and if
you're working in a field where that's
important you know you can't get around
that like that financial data can't even
hit any third party service apparently
even in in the office the people who
have access to that are kind of Walled
off because what they have can like
impact the market so yeah but they were
able to achieve very high accuracy and
also quite quickly by approaching the
problem in like you know kind of a a
smart way and also reasoning about
things again like I feel like I I keep
saying this in a lot of other contexts
like oh you just you know you need to
sit down and reason about stuff because
and I think well it's not the most
attractive answer or piece of advice
because you know you still need to sit
down and reason about stuff but
ultimately I think that's what a lot of
it comes down to in software development
in AI the best practices we've learned
about how to build software still apply
and it's not all changing because
Suddenly It's AI yeah so I I think in
this specific case they're looking at
these spans of tax and then I don't know
if they're Financial analysts or
something like that but they have all
these categories or ways to classify
what they're looking at yeah it's like
there's this price at which something is
traded and here's like this is about the
crude oil market and then this is the
location of some port in China wherever
where something like even though a lot
of Finance is so digital there are some
areas that like ton of stuff happens
where so much money is moved that is
then shockingly physical where like yeah
you suddenly have some port in somewhere
in the world but then you also have
other stuff about carbon credits and
that is just an example from finance and
it was it was just kind of fresh in my
mind but there's like a lot of that in
probably any area you can think of like
any specific domain there's like a lot
of that data that's also that's specific
and not generic and not general purpose
and that makes it hard to work with but
of course also a lot more valuable in
something that is a lot more general
purpose so know in this case it could be
things like the location the financial
Market the product or item that they're
talking about even though I have looked
at this and thought about it and have
been writing it up to present to people
it's like it is abstract and I don't
even remember all the stuff that it's
about so for that use case or also for
the people who consuming that data and
the customers they you know want to
consume this feed as quickly as possible
see what's happening in a structured
format be able to do analysis of it feed
it into their system and then yeah make
decisions about the market the market
becomes more transparent in the process
so that's all yeah very important but
yeah it's also very specific and yeah
then there other use cases we have I
think one we've also published around
jism there's in data media content
creation there's like a bunch of stuff
around that where you have user
generated content so you don't even know
what you're going to get but you want to
be able to classify that detect bad
behavior detect how you can classify
label something basically make the work
that normally humans would do more
efficient not even necessarily replace
humans but make humans better and faster
at their work yeah and the user
generated example I could see someone
looking at social media posts maybe and
being able to pull out okay what's the
the subject and are they speaking
positively about something or are they
attacking someone or you know basically
being able to figure out what's this
person talking about and are they
violating our policies in some way which
brands up people talking about how are
people talking about my brand our
competitor or I don't know some other
industry that's all important and that's
also where having a model that's a bit
more accurate actually makes a big
difference because you're finding out
more and you're also finding out things
you didn't already know ideally like if
you're you know really working with data
in a good way you actually you're
interested in the stuff you don't
already know and not just use it to
confirm things you've suspected at least
that's where you know it really starts
becoming valuable yeah and in this case
and this kind of goes back to the
predictive part you were talking about
earlier is as software developers we're
used to working with structured data
we're used to working with data we can
put into a database and we have all
these properties or attributes we know
about it versus if you have unstructured
text it's very difficult to get any kind
of insight into it because you need to
be able to extract all the information
out first so yeah and I think it's also
still important like having databases
and having I mean even if you think back
to even before computers like what were
companies doing people were categorizing
stuff on index cards and there's this
tremendous value in structure and that's
also why I think this is also not going
away like you know you might see some
hot takes of people saying well if we
now have these massive large language
models that can just generate stuff we
just feed them all over our text and
then we can ask it questions about it
and there are a lot of use cases where
that's like pretty exciting and really
adds a lot of value but it's not
necessarily you know companies are not
going to throw out all their databases
that they've been work working on since
before they had computers and all the
structure they have and like replace
that with some black box that you know
PO is much slower less accurate and more
expensive than what they currently have
like that's not how new developments in
the field will impact industry it's like
it's a lot more nuanced and in a way
actually much more exciting than that
let's touch on that a little bit more
because you gave some of the examples of
where a special Iz model is set because
you said you can run it locally you have
trained it yourself with your own
examples so you have a better sense of
that it's it maps to your expectations I
suppose but where are the the areas
where a large language bottle is like
good for this kind of pipeline or or
what are the kinds of problems where
they are good in this case yeah so it's
always a trade-off but it's usually you
know it's also not like an either or
question like it's mostly you know you
can combine the different Technologies
so one thing of course where especially
a lot of the latest models that have
come out are really adding capabilities
that we couldn't do before that's really
around the text generation so being able
to accurately summarize a text for
example that used to be like not that
great and that like took a lot of work
to get that to to at least be okay and
now this is pretty good so if you have a
workflow where you have a long document
you want to summarize that and then
extract things from the summary which is
much easier to work with that's
something where taking a large
generative model really does something
that we couldn't do before and there's
also the aspect of getting started and
really prototyping quickly before we
always had this problem that there is
this bottleneck in the initial data so
before you have a model that predicts
something and gives you an idea of does
this idea of how I've structured this
problem does it make sense is this a
like basically what we talked about
before you sit there reasing about
things come up with a way to break it
down and to test that you need at least
a few hundred examples that are also
good and if you really do it properly
that's like easily 40 hours of work
maybe that you put into that before you
have a model that predict something and
it's probably quite and then maybe at
the end of it you train your model and
the accuracy is zero then you have to
figure out what's what's the problem is
it because my data is bad did I forget
some hyperparameter did I have a bug in
my car Cod like it's that part is very
frustrating and that is something where
very easily Now with an existing model
an API you can get to a system that's
kind of okay and lets you have a
prototype and test out your things
almost instantly with the right tooling
around it so for example for Spacey we
have the Spacey llm library that
provides all of these components in the
pipeline but powered by a large language
model for example via open in API or
locally and so you have the same
predictive Behavior but the model and
the functionality comes via a prompt
from the large language model and so in
minutes you can have something running
that you can then improve and then you
can also test does it work at all how
does it work on my data and that's a
huge Improvement and then you can see
which parts you can also mix and match
maybe there are some things where where
it's a very generalizable general
purpose task where a large general
purpose model does really well and you
want to keep that and then there's maybe
something else where you realize
actually you've spent all this time
trying to predict it but you cannot get
better than a regular expression that's
also often a realization you have to
make or why it why it pays off to have a
baseline because yeah you might spend a
lot of time in and realize yeah okay
this is yeah you can't get better than a
regx and so it sounds like when you're
working on a NLP type task you have all
these different tools available to you
you have like you said you even said
regular Expressions you can try you have
these models like where you're you're
giving examples and I would call it like
transfer learning so that's really the
idea you start off with some weights
that have been pre-trained on Raw text
so you start off with some knowledge
about the language and the world and you
don't have to train it from scratch so
that's something you know kind of these
bird siiz models maybe people have heard
about and the idea here is you still
train something specific but you start
off with a lot of knowledge and then now
we also have in context learning which
is you know a lot of those large
language models that people know from
the GPT family for example especially
the later models that are released where
you can use a text based prompt to
control the behavior and then you get
text out usually and yeah those are kind
of the the different options and
they're good for different things and
you can combine them for even better
workflows and it sounded like what you
were saying earlier too is that you
might start with using a large language
model to solve a specific problem and
then based on that you might decide like
oh it's it's good enough I can just use
this or you might see it and go like
well the accuracy is not that good so I
need to go and do some additional like
tuning of a model yeah or you can use it
to create data for you as well like
that's actually a lot of experiments
we've been running where we're trying to
test how many examples do you need and
how quickly can you generate them
actually using the llm in the loop as
well to generate the examples so you
only make Corrections which is super
fast and then how long does it take
until you can train a model that reaches
the same accuracy because once you get
there you have like a lot of other
benefits you have a model that does
exactly one thing so you don't have to
you also don't have to worry about like
all these you know you have all these
other parts of the model that you don't
need and maybe there's unexpected
Behavior it's very very difficult to
predict so you have a model that really
only outputs yes or no or it outputs in
a way of numbers and that's it that's
what it does and it that means it can be
much much smaller so again you can have
like a powerful pipeline in production
that's 6 megabytes for the whole thing
and then it can run at 10 K words per
second depending on how you've build it
but even a th000 words per second is
pretty good if you're processing things
on a large scale and your model can be
entirely private so you know not no data
needs to leave your service it can run
offline don't even need internet for it
it can run on your local MacBook you can
even sometimes train it on your local
MacBook if you have like a modern
processor and yeah if you can get to a
model that you can actually make better
that's like you know you really have the
best of both worlds and I think
especially as the technology develops
which makes for example larger and
larger models possible at the same time
that it also makes us able to use
compute much more efficiently so that
means we can also go the other route and
try to go smaller and faster and better
and that's I think an area that's almost
more exciting and more useful for
practical contexts than seeing how large
we could get that's also an interesting
area but that's also I find it a bit
less rewarding than saying okay how can
we break that down more and make it more
practical that's where also where apis
make sense because you know you have
like yeah companies like open AI they
can batch up the requests there's a lot
of stuff you can do at scale that let
you make these API calls cheaper but you
could not provide that if you were
running it locally so it makes sense to
have it as an API or like you have
different providers but of course then
you always have the problem of calling
an external API you have the data
privacy question you also have the
latency things are getting faster but
it's still making an API call takes a
while you might have like one word per
second for some cases that's okay for
other cases you can't work with that and
yeah also the general reliability
question of no API provider will be able
to provide every model ever they have to
even open AI has to retire old models
otherwise that's like already I don't
know how how many millions it costs to
keep like a model app but if you're
using an older version the model may
change and even if the model is overall
performing better and people are
reporting better results for your use
case it might be that whatever changed
just suddenly makes it worse so it's
like you know it's like it's like how in
software you want to pin your
dependencies in some way you want to
make sure that like you can reproduce
that and that does become a lot harder
if you don't own the model weight so
it's it's kind of It's Always a
trade-off but I think also it is
possible to get around that and work
around that like the future is not just
like bigger and bigger black boxes like
that development also enables kind of a
whole counter development that's a good
point about pinning dependencies because
I've I've heard people talk about the
open AI GPT models where the version of
the model hasn't changed but people
report like oh it's not giving me the
same aners it was before yeah and an
open AI say well we didn't change the
model and technically that might be
correct because they might have changed
some other logic because again that it's
also not public like you have a general
idea of how the system works but you
don't know what else happens and since
it's an API there also has to be a lot
of sanitizing and just working around
really bad use cases and so many
different layers so yes something else
might have changed not the actual model
but it still changes and you can't know
what changed because you can't look
inside yeah there was a recent example I
thought was pretty interesting where
there were people saying like oh during
the holiday time frame it felt like the
model wasn't performing as well and
there was a theory that perhaps it was
because the internally the model is
adding the current date to The Prompt so
that it knows when you're making the
request and maybe that was influencing
the results so it's it's interesting
when you you don't have full insight
into what's happening yeah yeah yeah
that is an interesting well and also
this point out how important it is to
really have an evaluation set like I'm
often like surprised how you know many
people gloss over that fact because you
know you don't want to test your model
by just like typing something in or
trying it and seeing how you feel about
it that's another thing it's like I'm
sure a lot of also researchers who
report these things about the models
they actually do have an evaluation that
they run and then they can say well
today the model definitely performed 5%
worse but if you're not doing that then
you're just like ah it feels like today
chat GPT is giving me worse answers but
you can't quantify that you know that
works if it's just like you know you
privately asking it questions about
coding or something but if this is like
your production system that's worth a
lot of money or that delivers a lot of
value that's not how you want to
evaluate it yeah and open AI they even
publicly responded where they said like
oh we've been hearing these reports that
the model seems lazier or something like
that yeah but I mean what
yeah very very hard to evaluate against
that yeah so I think that's also why you
want to be able to do better than that
when it's really about your product and
about you know what your company is
doing yeah and I think it was
interesting that you mentioned how to
help train a model you need all these
examples and you could use a large
language model to generate the example
or to add the structure to do the stuff
you otherwise would have to do by hand
yeah yeah and so would that be like if
if the example was if we needed a bunch
of user reviews that we were going to
train on that you would have the large
language model generate the review and
then give you a first pass at annotating
it or I'm trying to understand my
suggestion was mostly annotating you
have a lot of raw data but you need a
lot of examples of reviews that where
you specifically highlight the products
in those reviews and you've scraped them
all but you know you want to be quicker
and you don't want to do it manually so
then you can actually for example you
can use something like Spacey llm for
example that really that gives you the
structured output or in our annotation
tool Prodigy we have workflows for that
where it basically just streams that in
and you just say yes or no or maybe make
a slight correction when it's wrong
there is also synthetic data is another
huge area where you know you're really
generating the text and for some things
that can work especially you know if you
can Define the constraints around what's
possible but of course you also have a
risk there of like feeding model
generated data back into the model and
you need to know that it's actually
representative of what your model will
see at runtime otherwise there's kind of
no point in doing that so but I think
The annotation part is definitely
something that you can really use the
model for and then if you combine that
with something like transfer learning
where you're starting off with
pre-trained weights that already know
things you can actually get to a point
where you only really need a few hundred
examples and that's not a lot that is
something you know even an individual
developer or small team can just do
you're not at this point anymore where
you need to think about large scale
annotation efforts and Mechanical Turk
and hiring a bunch of Click workers
stuff like that that is all something
that got massively disrupted by
technology and I think it's good because
I do think the practices around you know
the whole Mechanical Turk Market
that was already Shady you had like
people doing this work for I don't know
$2 an hour $5 yeah or less and then
creating this data with no connection to
the task that's not what you need you
want subject matter experts domain
experts like imagine having Financial
analysts medical professionals being
able to have them in the loop and help
you with the data and if you make the
process efficient enough then you can do
that and that's really great and then
that really puts the data where it
should be so it sounds like instead of
generating the examples you would scrape
them or get your own collection and then
you would use the large language model
to do a first pass at annotation so that
when you have your experts or your
people looking them over they don't need
to start from scratch they can see like
oh all these things have already been
annotated and they look right and I can
just click the green checkbox yeah yeah
or there even you know can take it one
step further and maybe even have a model
or some algorithm that maybe tries to
sort them in a way that you start off
with those that are maybe most important
or that the model is less certain about
or that look different from the others
and so you can actually Focus the
human's time on probably the ones that
need more attention than the others so
there's a lot you can do as part of that
process and yeah especially also many
people start off by having the raw data
like that's why the data generation and
synthetic data is like a Big Field but
often the kind of main bottleneck or
problem is that you're sitting on all
this raw data or you're sitting on
another example company reports and
internal reports and stuff people have
written like we've amassed so much text
over decades that are all sitting around
somewhere on computers and you have all
this stuff and you want to analyze it in
a structured way and so there's no
shortage of raw data but the hard part
is deciding what you want to do with it
how to even Define the structure and
then creating examples where you know
the answer or translating it into a
prompt for first pass which is also
tricky because you know again the easy
part is it's accessible you can just
write instructions but in a lot of cases
that also ends us back kind of where we
started before machine learning where
you have to define a lot of rules and
have to write down this whole manual
thinking of all edge cases and that's
where get to a point where hey actually
it's a lot easier to just give it a few
examples in context that show the
nuances of language and so you were
talking a little bit earlier about how
before people would have to it sounds
like maybe train a model from scratch
where you needed lots of examples and
that's why you're referring to the
Mechanical Turk and hiring all these
people to do these annotations for you
but then you mentioned like now we have
transferred learning and there's some
models you can just take off the shelf
and maybe do a little bit of tuning give
a few examples and get the results you
need are there like a few specific
examples of those models that like I
guess you know within the last 5 or 10
years have really made it easier to
solve these kinds of problems yeah so
mostly you know what I'm referring to
here is like you basically start off
with the representations of the words
and then what you train on top is really
just the layer or the part that does the
specific thing so you start off with for
every word you know you have like this
Vector for it that sort of in context
represents what it means in you know
different scenarios so you've built up
these huge representations and that
actually turns out to really improve
your model across all kinds of tasks so
that's this whole idea that really was
popularized with Bert the model from
Google and the paper and this idea that
if you train a system to predict the
next word given the previous words you
build up representation of the words in
context as sort of this side product
that are really really useful for all
kinds of other things because it turns
out that by doing that you're building
up this knowledge this abstract
knowledge that really contains a lot
about the language in the world Al so
all of these capabilities that the model
needs to learn to predict the next word
are also super useful for all kinds of
other things you're doing with text so
it's actually interesting because
speaking of like specific models because
for a while there was like The Surge of
so many different you know of what
people now call Foundation models which
you know really just provide these
representations there was like a new one
every day and a lot of different things
happening or researchers trying out
different things but I feel like at this
point the community really has like
converged on a very small set of models
often in the bird family that have
consistently done well and that everyone
is using so even something like this
Roberta B A lot of these kind of family
models also for different languages for
different that is usually what works the
best and the Really the general purpose
pre-trained weights but also you can
train these things yourself and there
are even ways to train these word
embeddings and word representations in a
way that doesn't cost tons of compute if
you have a lot of raw text you just let
it run over your raw text and build up
these representations using the same
language modeling approach predicting
the next word and then you can even do
that for your really specific data if
you're you know sitting on millions of I
don't know regulatory documents or you
have your specific legal stuff or some
biomedical drug trial report things like
all this kind of stuff you're sitting on
all these millions of documents you can
pre-train your own embeddings
and then use transfer learning and then
you only need hopefully very few
examples to really add that layer that
tells it what specifically it should do
so these models that I suppose descended
from ber they have an understanding of
maybe General language but then what
you're adding on top of that is an
understanding of your specific domain
whether that's Finance or yeah or use
specific task like extract this thing or
these labels and yeah and before we had
transfer learning you kind of had to do
all of that from scratch and that was
even harder and that's also where this
idea of armies of annotators came from
because it's really it's kind of like
the concept of getting a new employee
and training them versus raising them
from birth even though it's it sound
kind of a creepy example but you know
before you really had to raise this
model from birth and like teach it
everything if you wanted it to predict
what's a verb and what's a noun you had
to give it so much data that it like
learned all of that and now you can
actually start off with a much larger
Foundation that way and also there's so
much context about the world and how
certain things are used together like
once you now get into this or really
think about how we use language there's
so much that's very arbitrary that makes
absolute sense to us in a super
intuitive but is really weird to a
computer at first and that changes too
so there is this
like these models have to change as well
or your models constantly have to evolve
because the world isn't static and
language isn't static and it sounds like
for someone who is new to this world I
mean we've talked a little bit about
spacey but it sounds like spacy itself
maybe has collected these different
models where somebody who has a specific
problem they can use Spacey and there's
apis available that are going to help
direct you toward towards which model
you should use that's the idea or even
Beyond model it's more about like well
the specific task or we really try to
focus on language and language specific
tasks because that's often how you know
also people who start out coming with an
NP problem think about it like you don't
usually think about it in terms of
vectors that come in and vectors that
come out and there's a lot in a lot of
more General machine learning contexts
language is treated like any other input
or any other vector and in Spacey we've
always try to present it with data
structures and with basically Concepts
that are about language so you really
have a doc object that holds the text
and you have words are split in a
linguistic way you know they also layer
down this split in the way that's most
computationally efficient but on the
surface you get actual words and then
from there you know you have components
for extracting entities for predicting
labels over text for applying rules and
so on and basically takes a very
opinionated approach because we don't
want to provide like five different
model implementations with different
trade-offs we want to find one that's
the best at least you know that's the
goal so we want to give you one best way
to do a thing that's kind of through the
whole library that idea so it sounds
like from the start like if I'm looking
at unstructured text and I don't have
something like Spacey I might start by
using regular expressions or split
statements to try and F figure out like
okay where are all the words and is this
a sentence and all that sort of thing
yeah and then you quickly realize that
like oh sentence let's split that on
periods and then you realize oh wow
there actually so many instances of the
period character across the language
that you never thought about and yeah it
starts from there and then on the other
end of the spectrum you can put your
text in chat GPT and ask it questions
about it yeah so it seems like a lot of
the work that everybody will have to
figure out if they're working with
natural language Spacey gives you the
data structures and apis where you're
working directly with I suppose the
linguistic Concepts or the like you were
saying you get the words you get the
sentences you have like data structures
for different you know connections of
words for different underlying labels
and you have you know we also provide
pre-trained pipelines that you can
download that are a general purpose that
you can start with and a lot of
documentation around how to break down
your problem but yeah the part where you
decide what you want is like sort of
that's inherently yours and that's also
something that someone else can't do for
you or you know you you shouldn't want
to lean on someone else to tell you like
what you should want you know maybe
people expecting that but I think also
especially if it's around a real world
use case a business problem or even a
hobby you're really passionate about
like you want to be the one you know you
need to be clear about what you want and
if you have a good idea or approach it
well then it's going to be successful
and if you want things that don't make
sense then you kind of you know you want
to get to a point where you figure that
out and adjust these things but I think
in in that sense it's like running a
business it's like writing any piece of
code or software and it's ultimately
still down to us making decisions
basically yeah I mean it's not a NLP
specific problem but it's like any type
of engineering challenge we take on we
have to break down what is the actual
problem we're trying to solve yeah yeah
exactly but I feel like people often
forget about this part when they come
into AI or NP because isn't it supposed
to be artificial intelligence and isn't
it supposed to just be magical because I
think often that is how it's presented
to us you know whether it's in the media
whether it's you know even by companies
trying to sell the AI so that people
come in with expectations that are maybe
not realistic about the work flows yeah
though I suppose with the large language
models it can sometimes get closer like
somebody can have a vague problem and
they put it into the llm and maybe it's
not perfect but it's like it's closer to
I have this vague idea in my head and I
get an output no exactly and I think
that is where text based prompts can be
quite helpful to like guide you through
that process and I think that also does
set a new standard for this is how easy
it is to get started but and then you
often kind of of hit a point where you
want to go beyond that and I think
what's interesting is okay how can we
bring that sort of experience that
people have with hey you can just sort
of get started be guided more easily can
you know you don't need to do any
preparation you don't need to really
understand the depth of machine learning
that's what prompts provide and how can
we bring that same experience not even
necessarily all just you know chatting
with a thing but more like this ease of
use to the quote unquote EXP workflow or
to the workflow that opens up more
possibilities which is working with
creating examples training your own
models for me that's kind of probably
the most interesting question I'm
thinking about and working on right now
and that's also kind of where our future
product is going like Prodigy teams
which sort of Builds on top of the idea
of creating labeled data as a way to
tell the system what to do but then sort
of bringing it into the cloud and making
it more accessible to people people who
don't come in with a strong developer
background it sounds like maybe the
start for somebody who doesn't quite
know specifically what they want they
just have a high level idea they might
start with using a large language model
and then see what results they get from
that but then based on that then they
can maybe work out can I break down my
problem into more specifically what I
want it's a little hard to describe but
the example you gave at the start was
about looking through news articles and
and figuring out like are these things
good or bad for my company I guess yeah
like first okay let's filter out the
noise then next let's extract I don't
know the areas and countries and cities
that I mentioned because then you can
match that up with cities you're doing
business with or cities you can match it
up with your supplier database and take
the locations where your suppliers are
and stuff like that and I think often
that is you know that's also something I
know you just have to think about it and
have those kinds of ideas and then you
know you also want to have this again
modularity that's also something we know
from normal software development and we
use that as a good approach because it
makes our systems more robust it makes
our systems easier to test easier to
understand and the same thing is true
for machine learning models as well you
don't want your whole pipeline to
completely depend on each other and you
want to be able to change one part of
the system without the whole other stuff
potentially falling apart and you want
to be able to evaluate each component
and not have it all be this one box and
so I think you know especially if
someone is coming into the field from a
more classical software engineering
background I would say like don't let
all of this AI stuff I don't know
distract you from like the right path
that you already have like there are a
lot of Concepts and things you know
about good software development that you
can apply and that definitely apply to
AI models as well yeah and you sort of
talked about this earlier but in the
context of when you're solving a problem
there may be Parts where you use a large
language model for some parts and then
use a more traditional model you can run
locally for other parts and so you build
up this pipeline it's kind of like
reusable functions or like you know I
think for a lot of these things they are
parallels in more General software
development like you try to separate
your logic out in to reusable functions
you know you try to not repeat yourself
you don't put everything into one
massive function into huge blocks of
conditional logic like things like that
you want to find the right level of
abstraction like you can easily think
everyone goes through this journey when
they you know start developing software
you learn this New Concept and then
you're like oh now I'm going to apply
this to everything and then you end up
with this code that's like so abstract
that you know it's completely impossible
to understand and then you kind of go
back and you're like ah wait now I went
too far the other way and those are yeah
those are the same kind of lessons that
you learn in machine learning and I
think yeah it's a lot less magic and a
lot more practical work with the data
and trying to find the best way to
define what you want that's really
always what it comes back to yeah it
seems like the part that's maybe unique
or different in this case is that when
you're making traditional software
applications it's deterministic in the
sense that you're writing line by line
and you're writing rules and you know
that okay if this happens then it'll go
on this branch and if not it'll go on
this Branch whereas this is more of a
I'm going to give the system examples of
what is right and then and then it will
try to make sense of it and predict
something and sure and I think actually
that brings up a good point of like how
is your application dealing with the
wrong predictions and again that is then
also that's not a machine learning
problem that really is an application
design engineering problem you know you
don't want to set up your system so that
any failure has like catastrophic
effects like you want to you to work
around that and sometimes people work
around that by not actually surfacing
any predictions to some end user but
having a human in the loop who then just
uses the output to help them and so on
there like a lot of you know a lot of
these questions around it but in a way
you want to use all this new technology
and kind of try to get back to a
situation that's as close as possible to
a deterministic solution that you're
used to from traditional software
development like you kind of want
something that's easy to control and
easy to predict and you want to reduce
complexity where you can because that
does make your system easier and you
know better to use and you know better
to work with and yeah that's another
thing people often forget if you're just
following research like if you are
actually implementing a practical
project for your own thing you are
allowed to make the problem easier for
you like in research you're trying to
find the hardest problems because
they're hard but like you are allowed to
make the problem easier if it is better
and solves the problem and that's also
where I think a lot is one by just
taking a step back and thinking you can
change the problem like just do
something else that gets you to the same
solution and if that's better and more
robust then that's a better solution do
you have a specific example and say like
you're work with customers where they
were trying to solve this problem that's
really difficult but you were able to go
like okay let's rethink what problem
we're actually trying to solve and make
that easier so one classic example it's
a bit comical once you like think about
it but it basically this was I think
some application about texts for I don't
know some court records and basically it
mentioned children and maybe it's about
custody or something like that and the
task was well we need to filter out the
names and dates of birth of children so
we can censor them and review it because
we don't want to I don't know publish
the names of miners so that's M classic
use case lots of data and so the first
initial approach they took was to
introduce two new categories and you
know translate the business problem so
one of them was child name and child
date of birth so at first glance okay
that really translates the business
problem and then you know you can go and
label all names of children and all the
dates of birth and then try to train a
model on it but of course if you take a
step back there's like nothing
inherently in a name that like you know
is a child or not it's just like a name
and also a date of birth the date of
birth of a child is defined by the date
being however you define like who an
adult is depends on the area but like
you know 18 years if their date of birth
is less than 18 years ago they a child
so if you actually included this in your
label scheme you basically try to teach
the model this distinction and try to
teach the model that and you can do it
with enough data and enough work you can
maybe make the model sensitive to that
information but it's a very roundabout
and of course much more difficult way of
framing the problem when instead you
could just be detecting dates and then
you take these dates you do some
normalization which you don't even need
machine learning for and then you do
maths in python or in whatever language
with the dates and then you can figure
out whether someone is a minor and it
has the added advantage that your model
isn't outdated tomorrow literally
because tomorrow people who are a minor
today will be an adult so you know again
it's like it's the thing where yes if
you hear that example people might laugh
and be like haha that's so obvious but
really thinking about it it is easy to
make these sort of steps in a direction
that really makes your problem a lot
harder than it should be especially
esecially once you get really deep into
the weeds of like something domain
specific and I think these mistakes
quote unquote are easier to make than
you might think and that's why I think
it's always important to yeah think of
these examples and evaluate your problem
and see am I making my life a lot harder
or can I just make the problem easier
yeah I think that makes a lot of sense
just in in general really like whenever
we're trying to solve a problem can we
break it up differently and like you
were saying
the more we can have using like
deterministic rules-based code versus
stuff that goes into a model that is a
little bit more opaque even if it does
go into a model like you kind of want to
still have it be as predictable as it
can and have like clearly defined scope
so you know okay that's where it can go
wrong and if it goes wrong here's kind
of what I can do about it so my whole
thing doesn't fall apart or all of your
components are separate and can be
separately improved so you know if this
component is struggling you can replace
that and improve that or maybe put a
more powerful model into that one
component and handle the other one
separately yeah cuz the smaller the
thing that is trying to accomplish
probably the easier it is to
troubleshoot yeah yeah yeah and also if
you have it in production like you
really want to analyze it and like you
want something that is operationally
simple or like you know you want to keep
the operational complexity low but yeah
for a lot of reasons and yeah if you can
do that for your model that's good just
the way it's good for any code you write
if you can achieve that point and I
think everyone has had that experience
of like I don't know you reacted some
piece of code or like you learn some
more stuff in the meantime and get write
some code and compare that to some other
stuff you've written you're like oh my
God how did I write that in such a
convoluted way when actually the
solution is so straightforward and yeah
it can be very similar for NLP and
machine learning so we haven't really
been specific about what languages that
we're talking about when we're talking
about natural language processing when
it comes to English versus Chinese or
all these other languages we have in our
world are the models specifically tuned
for certain languages and are the apis
and Spacey specific to languages or can
people kind of use them sort of in a
generic fashion
yeah so in general in NLP I think this
is rule of thumb the more similar
languages to English the better the
technology will genuinely perform
because a lot of it was developed for
English there are some models especially
nowadays that are kind of trying to be
language agnostic but especially for in
Spacey because you know we really also
try to focus a lot on the language and
the linguistic kind of view of like hey
here are words we found that often you
can achieve a lot by really focusing
more specifically
on the language and working with data
sets and also kind of exploiting what
specific languages need if you know you
come from like this English Centric view
separating text into words feels pretty
simple like you split on whites space
and then you add some rules around it
and that's it but then you know once
you're looking at Chinese for example
that's not an option and you really want
to have actually a statistical model
that predicts where words start and end
so that is also how Spacey solves that
at the moment so for Chinese you
actually need a statistical tokenizer
because yeah it's not really viable
otherwise and then they also in English
base forms of words are also pretty
simple with a few exception like
exceptions like you have I don't know
trees and then it's tree that's like you
know quite basic there also not so many
variations of that but if you go into
other languages even just creating a
word cloud really needs you to be able
to generate the base forms reliably and
that can be much trickier in a lot of
languages that have like inflected forms
and things that like the average English
speaker might not even think of or you
know or for example like my first
language is German we have like really
long words that people make fun of but
it's just you know you have like one
concept is one word and in English you
have like you have income tax
declaration something something and also
are separate words but it's like one
expression and this is like just the
basic stuff of like words and so I think
it's it's worth it to you know take a
look at like the specifics of the
language and actually find different
solutions and implementations that work
a bit better depending on what you're
doing but of course it all like stands
and falls with available data the one
thing we struggle with the most in
basically like we have a lot of
languages that we have basic support for
and you can train models but when it
comes to providing pre-trained pipelines
there's not always that much data
available and sometimes there is but it
comes from Academia and it doesn't have
commercial licenses and then we're like
me we can train something but nobody can
really use that because it's a library
for commercial use we don't want to
provide pipelines that are
non-commercial only so that is like a
big problem and that's also why never
really fully had time to focus on it but
like we've really want to always really
wanted to invest more into making more
premium models and actually just doing
our own data work and doing even just
doing annotation ourselves even for more
complex things across different
languages that can actually solve a lot
of problems for our users and for
general purpose pipelines are there
other companies that have done that that
have released premium models that people
have to pay for but kind of gives you a
head start I mean there's a lot of apis
that are you know sort of in that area
like I mean I know that there are
they've always been like yeah companies
developing private models but yeah I
don't know of any like exact exact
examples in like the open source space
but we've basically yeah we have these
pipelines that we distribute for free
but we actually have a survey on that
currently on the Spacey side to get like
you know sort of people's interest but
of course it does mean we need to invest
significantly into doing the work but
then we could provide these pipelines
for like a subscription and also keep
them updated I think that's actually one
area is H just create more data and
really build these specific models for
these generalizable linguistic tasks
that are better and then also keep them
updated because it's actually if you
think about it like a lot of these
corpor people are training on they're
like from 2005 or like a lot of them
there a lot of these current Concepts
that like the model has never seen and
it's like struggling with like something
like covid many you know even the more
newer systems and even like chat systems
around that time initially were
struggling because it you know Co had
been around for like I don't know a few
months at a time and no model has seen
Co and that's all we're potentially
interested in but again it's like this
is a lot more investment up front but at
the same time we've also think another
parallel line of work we've always done
is like trying to make it easier and
easier for people to train their own
system so even if you you know you can
start off using transfer learning with
spaces basic
tokenization for I don't know Arabic for
Chinese for Finnish and then start by
maybe plugging in a Spacey llm component
to just see how would it look if I
extracted person names how would it look
if I classified this text and then you
can try it and then you can take that
create some examples for it and then use
Spacey to train and then see okay how
far can I take this and when can I beat
my Baseline and then you basically have
this really tiny fast
private model that you can almost run on
your laptop and that's like a pretty
cool outcome yeah so it seems like maybe
the common flow would be you use an llm
like chat GPT or something to basically
build the prototype to see like okay is
this good enough and then if it's not
then that's when you would go and start
doing the transfer learning and yeah
exactly and that is also something you
can do within a Spacey pipeline so you
have to data structures and you really
have this object that you could work
with in your code and it behaves exactly
the same and it really also you know
it's all implemented in C extensions in
Python so it's like really fast you can
serialize it they're like basically all
these considerations around like good
data structures that you can I don't
know iterate over and work with and
store and convert and then you set that
up in your system in your API you maybe
plug in an llm component and then if you
had a point actually also Al do really
boring rule-based baselines I think I
mentioned this before try like a regular
expression see how far can you get with
a word list because you'd be surprised
and also like for some areas for some
use cases where people think oh my God
I'll never solve this I need so much
machine learning and it turns out that
actually of course computers are
efficient like if you think about I
don't know the number of all cities in
the US above a certain size I don't know
what I looked up the other but it's
actually not that many and it is
depending on what you're after for
example if looking at cities and in the
US or something you can provide a list
and it's no problem these days to match
over a list of 10K 20K 50k examples so
and you can download that off the
internet or from Wikipedia that list and
then you're done so there are these
things that are just interesting to try
for comparison because then you get you
can evaluate that and you get a number
at the end and then you know okay that's
what I want to beat and if your machine
learning model is worse then you know
me that's not really you're not quite
there yet yeah so don't underestimate
how fast computers are these days I
guess yeah and how how much you can
actually just do by Computing and also
even you know a lot of you know if what
you're doing can run in parallel which
is what a lot of you text extraction is
you actually you can run this on CPU
machines in the cloud and can just you
know run a lot of them that can be
significantly cheaper than say renting
out this expensive GPU machine and
running that in the cloud like there are
a lot of areas where you can optimize
and that's actually also why we've
always focused on also providing
workflows for CPU which is something
that like you know not many other
libraries in machine learning are doing
but we've actually seen that it makes a
difference and there are users that
really process like billions of words
with spacy and have found that well it's
just if I can run this on CPU it's just
a lot cheaper and I can still run it
really fast and yeah so there are all
these trade-offs that again it's just
like normal software development it all
still applies and just because there is
a new way to do a thing doesn't mean the
previous way goes away if anything often
the previous way gets better in the same
process and then you want to make sure
you're not forgetting about techniques
that are now much better well I think
that's a good place to end it on but is
there anything else you wanted to
mention or no I think I've talked a lot
I feel like we're also getting almost
philosophical at times so no cool so if
people want to check out what you're up
to or see Spacey or Prodigy where should
they head well our main website
explosion. has like an overview of
everything we're doing and also we
always like to Showcase things from the
ecosystem things other people publish so
I think that's the number one place to
go and then from there you can get go to
our Docs you can find me on social media
maybe say hi at some conferences you
know I'm trying to attend a bunch of
stuff again this year and I'll be
speaking at some conferences in Europe
so very cool well Ness thank you for
joining me on software engineering radio
yeah thanks again for having me this has
been Jeremy Jung for software
engineering radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team sc-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]